<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Theodore B. Barnhart (0000-0002-9682-3217)</origin>
        <origin>Andrew J. Long (0000-0001-7385-8081)</origin>
        <origin>Seth S. Haines (0000-0003-2611-8165)</origin>
        <origin>Brian Varela (0000-0001-9849-6742)</origin>
        <pubdate>20170918</pubdate>
        <title>Water use for hydraulic fracturing treatments in and near the Williston Basin, United States, 2000-2015</title>
        <geoform>GeoTIFF</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F78P5ZDV</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Water used for hydraulic fracturing treatments in and near the Williston Basin during 2000-2015, was estimated using data reported in IHS Markit (TM) (2016). Hydraulic fracturing treatment data from IHS Markit (TM) (2016) may include volumes in a variety of measurement units, and they may include multiple treatments per well. All listed treatments within the study area were converted to gallons and summed on a per-well basis, discounting any treatments for which the specified measurement units were unclear (for example, “sacks”, or “feet”), which were minor. Of 3,734,380 treatments listed within the study area during the timeframe of interest, 0.7% (26,373 records) were not included. For each well, the date listed as the well completion date (typically the date of final preparation of the well for petroleum production) was considered to be the date of the water consumption. Listings for the actual treatment date are incomplete in the IHS Markit (TM) (2016) database, but generally the completion date is within a few days, or at most months, of the actual treatment date. The per-well treatment volumes were then aggregated via summation to a 1-mile grid using ArcGIS functions. The annual aggregated hydraulic fracturing treatment data were exported as annual GeoTIFF images with a resolution of 1 square mile per pixel and bundled into a TAR archive file. This data is not part of the USGS Aggregated Water Use Database (AWUDS) or the National Water Information System (NWIS).</abstract>
      <purpose>The aggregated data were used to assess the amount of water used for hydraulic fracturing treatments in the Williston Basin during 2000-2015.  The data were used to simulate groundwater responses to increased withdrawals during a hypothetical 10-year drought (2006-2015) using a transient groundwater model (described in USGS Professional Paper 1841, available at http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/1841/).</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>2000</begdate>
          <enddate>2015</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Year of well completion</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-108.8021</westbc>
        <eastbc>-98.3290</eastbc>
        <northbc>50.8565</northbc>
        <southbc>44.4239</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>hydraulic fracturing</themekey>
        <themekey>water use</themekey>
        <themekey>well drilling</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
        <placekey>Williston Basin</placekey>
        <placekey>Montana</placekey>
        <placekey>North Dakota</placekey>
        <placekey>South Dakota</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Brian Varela</cntper>
          <cntorg>Southwest Region</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Mail Stop 939, W 6th Ave Kipling St</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-303-236-5747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>bvarela@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>IHS Markit (TM)</origin>
            <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
            <title>US Well History and Production Database</title>
            <geoform>database</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Englewood, CO</pubplace>
              <publish>IHS Markit (TM)</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>https://ihsmarkit.com/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>point</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20000101</begdate>
              <enddate>20151231</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>2000/01/01-2015/12/31</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>IHS</srccitea>
        <srccontr>IHS data were summarize in the one square-mile gridded data set presented herein.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Water used for hydraulic fracturing treatment associated with oil and gas production wells in and near the Williston Basin were collected from the IHS Markit (TM) database and aggregated to one square-mile totals for the years 2000 - 2015. The resultant gridded data set is: “treatment_water” - the volume of treatment water used per grid cell (one square mile) per year. Data were converted from their original geodatabase format (a fishnet vector object containing one square-mile polygons with attributes for the hydraulic fracturing treatment water for each year) to raster data (one raster for each year) using ArcPy (ArcMap version 10.4). These rasters were then re-processed using gdalwarp (gdal version 2.1.4, www.gdal.org) to make their nodata values and datatype uniform. The treatment_water data set is stored as Band 1 in each GeoTIFF raster.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20170824</procdate>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Theodore Barnhart</cntper>
              <cntorg>USGS WY-MT WSC</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
              <address>3162 Bozeman Ave</address>
              <city>Helena</city>
              <state>Montana</state>
              <postal>59601</postal>
              <country>United States</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1-406-457-5900</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>tbarnhart@usgs.gov</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>Williston Basin, United States, North America</indspref>
    <direct>Raster</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>Lambert Conformal Conic</mapprojn>
          <lambertc>
            <stdparll>33.0</stdparll>
            <stdparll>45.0</stdparll>
            <longcm>-104.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>0.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </lambertc>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>row and column</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>5280.0</absres>
            <ordres>5280.0</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.2572221010002</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Treatment Water</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Water used for hydraulic fracturing treatments</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Seth Haines (shaines@usgs.gov)</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Band 1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The volume of water in gallons used for hydraulic fracturing treatments per grid cell compiled from IHS Markit (TM) (2016).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Data from the IHS Markit (TM) US Well History and Production Database. Full citation: IHS Markit (TM), 2016, US Well History and Production Database: Englewood, Colo., IHS Markit (TM), accessed August 2016 at http://www.ihsenergy.com. [Available from IHS Markit (TM), 15 Inverness Way East, Englewood, CO 80112.]</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>311</rdommin>
            <rdommax>109235784</rdommax>
            <attrunit>gallons</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey - Science Base</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data for other purposes, nor on all computer systems, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.

Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform><digtinfo>
          <formname>TIFF</formname>
          <formvern>none</formvern>
          <formspec>GeoTiff</formspec>
          <formcont>A TAR archive containing the GeoTiff images and metadata.</formcont>
          <transize>30.0</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/599f48ece4b0e5eb065f7554</networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
    <techpreq>This data release contains GeoTiff images of hydraulic fracturing treatment volumes for each year. These data may be viewed and manipulated with a variety of software including the open source geographic information system QGIS (http://www.qgis.org).</techpreq>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20180911</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Theodore B Barnhart</cntper>
          <cntorg>United States Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>3162 Bozeman Avenue</address>
          <city>Helena</city>
          <state>MT</state>
          <postal>59601</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-406-457-5900</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tbarnhart@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
